<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a prnted pamphlet called the case of the inhabitants of Croydon in the county of Surrey, humbly offered to the Parliaments judicious consideration.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213143</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825642</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825642</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30028</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25544)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30028)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 1772:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a prnted pamphlet called the case of the inhabitants of Croydon in the county of Surrey, humbly offered to the Parliaments judicious consideration.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: The case of the inhabitants of the town and parish of Croyden in the county of Surrey.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clewer, William --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Case of the inhabitants of the town and parish of Croyden in the county of Surrey.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Attachment and garnishment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Croyden (London, England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30028:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to a printed Pamphlet called the Caſe of the Inhabitants of <hi>Croydon</hi> in the County of <hi>Surrey,</hi> Humbly offered to the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Judicious Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
            <p>TO all unconcern'd perſons who have known the people of <hi>Croydon,</hi> and time out of mind their un-Chriſtian dealing with the Reverend <hi>Dr. Bernard</hi> (the laſt legall Incumbent, whom they Sequeſtred,) and all the reſt of their Miniſters, it might Suffice to ſay, their Uncharitable and inhumane Pamphlet is a Libel, but ſuppoſing it may be peruſ'd by Straingers, In generall it will ſeeme incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible to any Conſiderate man, that if he had beene guilty of thoſe Crimes they pretend, being all or moſt part alledg'd to be done by him above Ten Years ſince, that they had not (while in memory) convicted him of one of them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many years vſ'd all means that Violent and Unreaſonable men for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verige, could poſſibly invent.</p>
            <p>And though he can patiently beare the malice of thoſe who neither frequent Church or Sacraments, And who in ſeveral other Courts if their Oaths had been regarded, and by the mercy of God he had not falſified, would long ſince have ruin'd him. Yet for the Satisfaction of his Friends and impartiall Perſons who deſire to be further undeceived, its anſwered, That <hi>Mr. Whitford</hi> was by ſome of the late Powers ſequeſtred from his Living, And one <hi>Mr. Seymor</hi> by his Conſent put into the ſame, who by the Conſent of the ſaid <hi>Mr. Whitford</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned it to <hi>Dr. Clewer</hi> and by agreement the <hi>Dr.</hi> did allow him 20 <hi>l. per Ann.</hi> though by the rules of the then Powers he was not lyable to pay any thing in regard he had a Temporal Eſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and no Child, and the living was worth but about 80 <hi>l. per Annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Allegations relating to <hi>Mr. Preſton,</hi> the <hi>Dr.</hi> found him there, and did never refine him for his Curate, but the ſaid <hi>Mr. Preſton</hi> (taking advantage of his abſence) did of his own accord then officiate as Curate, but the Major of <hi>Northampton</hi> adjudged him to be of a Scandelous life, and convicted him of Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſs for which he paid his Fine, and the <hi>Dr.</hi> being threatned to be Sequeſtered if he employed him, did forbid him, But contrary thereunto there being a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of eaſe belonging to the Church: He did Voluntarily officiate there, And after Commenced ſeverall ſuites againſt the <hi>Dr.</hi> under Colour of Wages; But the <hi>Dr.</hi> was never Plantive againſt him in any Suite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor proſecuted him for reading Common Prayer, The <hi>Dr.</hi> in thoſe times ſo far as it was ſafe for him frequently uſing the forme thereof, in Baptiſms and otherwiſe, particularly <hi>Mr. Howe</hi> a Miniſters Child of <hi>Cheſſamboys</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks, Sir Tobee Terryl,</hi> and <hi>Mr. King</hi> being Godfathers.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:30028:2"/>
            <p>As to the Articles therein pretended to be preferred againſt him as Miniſter of <hi>Aſhton,</hi> which muſt be above 20 Years ſince, the <hi>Dr.</hi> neither knows or remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers them, and its very ſttrange if it ſhould be true that the Authors of that Libellous Pamphlet were not acquainted when, and to whome they were exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, but if they had been as much lovers of truth as Calumny they would have alſo inſerted, That a parcell of Articles exhibited againſt him to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for Plundred miniſters, the Principall Charges whereof were, for neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to keepe publique faſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, thanksgivings, and other Contempts of the then Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, And afterwards, the <hi>Dr.</hi> being in a poſſibility of obtaining a better benefice, <hi>viz.</hi> A Rectory of 160 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> Another Complaint was made againſt him to the then <hi>Lord Fleetwood</hi> for praying in publique for the King, which hindred him of that intended Promotion; And that he did ſo pray for his Majeſty, And at that time when it was treaſon to do it, He hath very good proofe; But as to the perticular charges in thoſe Articles by the Pamphleter, the <hi>Dr.</hi> is not guilty of any of them, but is able (if though fit after ſo long a time) to make it evidently appeare he never Commenced any ſuite againſt any one there but upon very juſt and great provocation, and the law was alwayes for him.</p>
            <list>
               <head>As to the Charges againſt his life and Converſation,</head>
               <item>The Firſt is a Notorious falſehood.</item>
               <item>The Second is the ſame, for he was lawfully Married to Mrs. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and ſo lived together for above 20 Years.</item>
               <item>The Third is alſo a falſe aſperſion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>To that Paragraph concerning his coming into <hi>Croydon,</hi> The <hi>Dr.</hi> left <hi>Aſhton</hi> about a Yeare before his Majeſties happy Reſtaration, and never uſed any manner of Siniſter meanes for the obtaining of <hi>Croydon,</hi> nor made any ſuch promiſe as therein is charged.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Dr.</hi> was in the Yeare 60 Preſented to the Vicaridge of <hi>Croydon</hi> which is 30 miles in Compaſs, conſiſts of about 600 Houſe-holders, 3000 Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, and worth about 200 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> Yet the <hi>Dr.</hi> for the Two firſt years he lived there (depending on the Peoples Charity) could not receive beſides what ſome of the Gentry gave him (whoſe Tythes were very inconſiderable) above 5 <hi>l. per Annum:</hi> And he being unwilling to ſue his Pariſhoners let all his Tythes (excepting the Gentry) to one Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> for 60 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> who by reaſon of their Contention was in 3 years time 60 <hi>l.</hi> in arrears of the ſaid Rent, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Dr.</hi> let the ſame to <hi>George Plaw Senior</hi> (the greateſt farmer in the Pariſh) at the ſame Rent, who (repenting his bargaine) would not ſeale the Leaſes, but engaged ſeveral of his Friends (to perſwade the <hi>Dr.</hi> to diſcharge him of it, ſaying the Pariſhoners would not pay him without trouble, and to ſue them would ruine him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Afterwards <hi>John Blake</hi> Junior offered to take them at the ſaid rate, and entred into an agreement with the <hi>Dr.</hi> to ſeale the Leaſes within a fortnight af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who notwithſtanding did refuſe to do the ſame for the reaſon aforeſaid, then the <hi>Dr.</hi> deſired the Pariſhoners to make him 60 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and rate it according to the poors Booke, where upon ſeveral of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try meeting the veſtry, and choſe ſome of the Pariſhoners to make the ſaid rate,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30028:2"/>but his Adverſaryes refuſed to ſtand to it, whereupon the Gentry adviſed him to ſue them, He having often demanded his Tythes of them by ſending to every man a printed Ticket in this forme, A B. I deſire you to pay your dues in arreares to prevent charges and trouble to me, <hi>William Clewer.</hi> And many of them being above Seaven yeares in Arreares, and he (having no other preferment) was at laſt neceſſitated leaſt he and his Family ſhould have ſtarved (as ſome of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors almoſt were,) to ſue ſeveral of them, Thereupon they firſt exhibited Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles againſt him in the Spiritual Court, the principall whereof was, That he did not within Two months after Induction read the 39 Articles, and got Four Witneſſes to prove it, <hi>viz. Robert Wood</hi> Taylor, <hi>Thomas Brigſtock</hi> Husbandman, <hi>William Turlo</hi> Gardner, and <hi>William Cumber</hi> Pariſh-Clerk, the three firſt Swore he did not to the beſt of their Remembrance, but the Clerke Swore poſitively that he never read them till three years after he was Inducted, but the <hi>Dr.</hi> produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Mr. <hi>Sherman,</hi> the Church-wardens, and ſeveral other Credible Witneſſes, and likewiſe a Certificate under the Clerkes own hand, (which Mr. <hi>Pynſent</hi> one of his Majeſties Protonotories prooved his Confeſſion of,) That the <hi>Dr.</hi> read them within a fortnight after Induction, ſo that upon a full hearing he was acquitted by Sir <hi>Gyles Sweit</hi> then Dean of the Arches, who gave him Coſts for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They Indicted him at the Seſſions for not reading the Act againſt Swearing, where the Juſtices fined him but Sixpence, they being Satisfied it was a Malitious proſecution.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They Indicted him for taking money at the Sacrament, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to his own uſe, which he traverſed, but none would appeare againſt him, and ſo was diſcharged by Proclamation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, In <hi>Eaſter-Term</hi> 24th <hi>Caroli Secundi</hi> they preſerred an Information againſt him for Barretry in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> (though he never ſued but one Perſon for any thing but Tythes) to which he pleaded. And in <hi>Trinity-Term</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they moved for a Tryal at Bar, but upon hearing Councell on both ſides, and long debate, it was denied, and expreſly Ordered that it ſhould be tryed at the Aſſizes in the long Vacation, where the <hi>Dr.</hi> attended with his Witneſſes but they would not go on, then the day before <hi>Michaelmaſs-Term</hi> 24th the <hi>Dr.</hi> giving them notice he would try it by Proviſo the next Aſſizes, they mooved for a tryal at Bar, which (being done by the <hi>Kings-Councell</hi>) could not be denyed, and therefore granted accordingly, and ſet up one <hi>William Rolfe</hi> (a poore fellow, a <hi>Bayliffs</hi> follower) as Proſecutor, declaring they knew they could not prove it, but they would do it to diſgrace him, and put him to greater charge, and they put up Scandalous Papers againſt him in <hi>Croydon</hi> at the Market-Houſe and cauſed the <hi>Common-Cryer</hi> on a Market, day to make this Proclamation, O yes, All man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Perſons who have any thing to ſay againſt <hi>Dr. Clewer,</hi> or have paid him any Tythes, are deſired to repare to the Signe of the <hi>Herne,</hi> and they ſhall have thanks for their paines, and ſo God ſave the <hi>King.</hi> One <hi>Richard Heighden</hi> (a <hi>Bayliff</hi>) was the Maſter of that <hi>Ale-Houſe,</hi> who went up and down the Pariſh to enquire what every one gave the <hi>Dr. viz.</hi> To one Mr. <hi>Ruſſel Alſop,</hi> Mr. <hi>Edmund Gilpin,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Henry Piggot,</hi> who refuſing to ſatisfie him therein, he there upon warned Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi> to ſerve on the Grand Jury at the next Aſſizes held at <hi>Kingſton</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:30028:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Edmund Gilpin</hi> (being then about 67 years of age,) to ſerve on the Jury for Life and Death, and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Piggot</hi> being above 60 yeares of age to ſerve on the Jury of <hi>Niſi prius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was a rule of Court, That they ſhould give the <hi>Dr.</hi> a note of Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and name an able Proſecutor which not being done, (though often deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) Mr. Attorney General entred a <hi>Noli Proſequi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Dr.</hi> never made any ſuch agreement as is pretended, with Mr. <hi>Bickeeton,</hi> or gave him any note for the payment of 10 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they preſented a paper of greivances to his Grace of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (too long here to be inſerted) unto which the <hi>Dr.</hi> gave ſuch an anſwer that the Libellers thought good not to mention them.</p>
            <p>Being diſmiſt at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> they petitioned his Majeſty in Councell where they exhibited ſome Articles purporting the ſame in the Libell, who ordered them to give the <hi>Dr.</hi> a particular of their Charge, which they never did, Yet brought up their Witneſſes which were then heard, and the <hi>Dr.</hi> was promiſed another day to give in his anſwer, but inſtead thereof the whole matter was referred to his Grace of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Lord Chancellor to call before them the <hi>Dr.</hi> and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal of the Pariſh to ſettle a quiet maintenance for the Vicaer there, which if their Lordſhips could not effect, to report what was fit for his Majeſty to do therein.</p>
            <p>Upon which Order they cauſed the Belis to ring, and Bone-fires to be made at <hi>Croydon,</hi> giving out in Speeches, That the King ſhould ſay the <hi>Dr.</hi> was not fit to Preach, nor ſhould he any more, and that they had turned him out of his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and cauſed the common Cryer to make O yes, That if any Perſon ſhould pay the <hi>Dr</hi> any more tythes, they ſhould be hanged.</p>
            <p>As to that which concerns the Act of Grace, its an aſperſion that none but ſuch Scandalous Pamphleters durſt have tooke upon them.</p>
            <p>At their Oaths at Councell Table thoſe which the <hi>Dr.</hi> anſwered upon the Reference to his Grace and the Lord Chancellor are omitted, the reſt they (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Dr. could not diſprove) have miſreported, though what was thee-Sworne malitiouſly by intereſted Perſons, (either thoſe who were indebted to him, or whome had ſued for Tythes,) is anſwered as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward Humfry</hi> gave evidence he gave the <hi>Dr.</hi> four ſhillings to help him into the Almes-Houſe.</p>
            <p>For anſwer hereunto, he was really indebted to the <hi>Dr.</hi> 7 <hi>l.</hi> for Security where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be entred in a Judgment by conſent aboate a yeare before he came into the Alme-Houſe, and about half a yeare after he was in, the Governors ordred him to pay the <hi>Dr.</hi> 4 ſhillings which is all be ever paid of the ſaid 7 <hi>l.</hi> to this day, nor did he help him in, or turn him out.</p>
            <p>To the Second, That Sir <hi>Gyles Sweit</hi> late Deane of the Arches declared to the Churchwardens that the third part of the money collected at the Sect was the Viccars right, as appears by their Certificate, yet he neves Converted it to his owne uſe, but did always diſpoſe of it among the poor, though one of the <hi>Doctors</hi> proſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utors would have had one of the Churchwardens to have Sworn it, who telling him he could not, he Swore it himſelf.</p>
            <p>To the Third, That M. <hi>Benjamin Preſton,</hi> (the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Preſtons</hi> Son) did about<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 13 years ſince come to the <hi>Doctors</hi> Houſe to demand money of him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30028:3"/>for his Fathers officiating for him in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> the <hi>Dr.</hi> refuſed to pay him having never employed his Father, or owed him any thing, but neither ſent for him, or arreſted him.</p>
            <p>To the Fourth, That nothing of that was prooved, as is falſly alledged, and that Perſon whome they pretend was the <hi>Doctors</hi> ſpeciall <hi>Bayliff,</hi> and burnt in the hand, they produced upon a bearing in the Common Pleas as a Witneſſe for them, and that they never brought any to the <hi>Doctors</hi> Houſe but upon their own requeſt, nor was ever any kept Priſoner, or drawne into any Judgments in ſtead of pretended Notes, which the <hi>Dr.</hi> wonders they could have the confidence to affirme when it was manifeſtly debated in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> for many dayes, where the <hi>Judges</hi> not onely confirmed the Judgment which was greatly complained of, but gave the <hi>Dr.</hi> coſts for his unjuſt Vexation, The Court declaring he had done nothing but what became an honeſt man and a good Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>And they Sufficiently ſhew their malice in that they doe not onely ſlander the Dr. in his reputation, but all other perſons that appeare for him,</p>
            <p>To the Fifth, The Libeller was much miſtaken in this proofe, One Swore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that one of the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctors</hi> Subpoenaes was raſed, but could not tell any of the Names that were in the ſame, whereas they are legible and free from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſures, and if any ſuch were, they ſhould have complained of it in the Court of <hi>Exchequer,</hi> which they never did.</p>
            <p>Nor was there a word of the Warrents prooved, only <hi>William Rolfe</hi> Swore that the Dr. tooke ſeaven ſhillings and ſix pence for a Subpoena, but could not name any but one <hi>David Burnel</hi> who is Dead, but he denyes he tooke it, but hath ſeveral times forgiven them all Charges, and ſometimes hath taken 1 <hi>s.</hi> or 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> and many times the debt too, the <hi>Dr.</hi> was a very honeſt man in the ſaid <hi>Rolfes</hi> eſteeme till he employed another, and then he ſaid he would be revenged of him.</p>
            <p>It was alſo Sworne by <hi>Timothy Hills</hi> (a violent Proſecutor of the <hi>Dr.</hi>) That the Church dores were ſhut up for a moneth together while he was at <hi>London</hi> minding his Law, whereas the truth is, the <hi>Dr.</hi> was never at <hi>London,</hi> or from his Pariſh a month, nor a fortnight together ſince he was Viccar of <hi>Croydon,</hi> till he broak his Leg, Nor abſent 13 Sundays theſe 13 years, and alwayes when he was, tooke care that his place might be ſupplied with prayers and preaching.</p>
            <p>To the Sixth, He never ſued any man but one, for any other cauſe but Tythes, though be hath had above an 100 cauſes of Actions of Treſpaſs againſt ſeveral Perſons, for their Cattle coming into his Orchard and Garden Yet he never brought any Action againſt any one of them.</p>
            <p>To the Seaventh, A Carryer being hired to bring the <hi>Doctors</hi> goods to <hi>London,</hi> a large Desk of his was broken open, and ſeveral things Of value loſt out of is, with a Bond and other Writings, which occaſioned him a ſuite in Chancery to his very great Damage, He never ſued for 190 <hi>l.</hi> pretended to be in the Desk, not hath any Satisfaction for his Goods and Writings to this day.</p>
            <p>To the Eighth, It was not Sworne as the Libeller alledgeth. Nor did he ever
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30028:4"/>heare any before pretended he ſpoiled the Schoole; Indeed one Swore Rents were much fallen, wherein he did (as in other things) a little ſtretch his Conſcience, they being ſo far from falling, that thoſe farmes which were formerly let for Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are now let for above 40 <hi>l. per Annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the other Branch of that Article, the aforeſaid <hi>Hills</hi> Swore, That when the <hi>Dr.</hi> preached there was not above 60 People at Church, which the Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler hath reduced to 10 or 12, but in the Afternoon when any body elſe preached there were 3 or 400, which is now enlarged to 6 7 or 800, Whereas the Pariſhoners have often declared their approbation of the <hi>Doctors</hi> Miniſtry, and he ſeldom peeacheth to ſo few as 60 People, ſeldom fewer then 2 or 300, though there are ſeveral Meeting-houſes in that Towne, and frequently Seaven or Eight ſcore have received the Sacrament of the <hi>Doctor</hi> in one day.</p>
            <p>To the laſt, Mrs. <hi>Cooling</hi> (one of a known Reputation) Swore, That her Husband told her That the <hi>Doctor</hi> had adviſed him to be devorced from her, and offered himſelfe to procure it: but its denied that any ſuch thing was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed, or offered by him, notwithſtanding the Complaints he made to the <hi>Dr.</hi> which he forbears to mention.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Doctor</hi> underſtanding his Majeſty had referred it to his Grace of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> and the late Lord Chancellor to heare his defence, he brought his Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and made out his Innocency ſo far as then their Lordſhips proceeded, but the Libellers would not endure any further anſwer, but brought other Perſons to prove new matter never before pretended; But thoſe Honourable Perſons propoſing a Separation which he heartily deſired, and hoping for ſome proviſion by the way of Exchange, he waited for the ſame.</p>
            <p>That for the ſcandal of the Book, It was a Sufficient anſwer to ſay, That ſuch perſons as conceale fellonyes are as equally Criminal as the Party, and the Trepans of ſuch Perſons being notorious in the City, this was no otherwiſe, for that the <hi>Doctor</hi> about the yeare 60 being in a Booke-ſellers ſhop in the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſeeing one paſs by whom he had buiſneſs with, ſtept out haſtily to ſpeake with him, no farther then the dore, thereupon the Apprentice of the ſhop charged the <hi>Doctor</hi> as if he would have carried away the Booke, hoping to have drawne him to a Compoſition, rather then ſuch a thing ſhould have beene Queſtioned, but the <hi>Doctor</hi> (knowing his innocency) refuſed to be Trepanned, and is able by Perſons of Quality to prove the Maſter was angry with his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and expreſt his ſorrow for his abuſe.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Libeller pretends the <hi>Doctors</hi> Wife ſhould pay money, He on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſerts what thoſe Sherks would have had, which if it had been true, had prooved them guilty of Smothering Felonies, which the <hi>Doctor</hi> doth deteſt.</p>
            <p>The great thing againſt the <hi>Doctor</hi> that ſeemed to ſtick with the late Lord Chancellor was, That after ſeveral ſuites he did not try the modus Decimandi which was the onely reall Controverſy betweene him and his Pariſhoners, and hein-forming his Lordſhip that he offered to try the Title with any of the Pariſh, and that be never waved it, but they refuſing he could not try it, and they had 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> years time to enforce a Tryal, which they never did, but one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30028:4"/>
               <hi>John Godden</hi> (another Proſecutor) pretending he offer'd to try it, the Dr. diſproov'd him by declaring that in the Suit between them he pleaded an agreement in lieu of all Tythes, ſo that the <hi>modus</hi> could not come in Iſſue.</p>
            <p>But the Dr. did then deny (as true it is) That his Grace did ever di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him not to try it before the Lord Chief Baron, for that he would never have fear'd the Juſtice of that Worthy Perſon.</p>
            <p>And the Dr. having manifeſtly diſprooved by Honourable Perſons many of the Scandalls they had charged upon him before the King and Councell; and being then ready to have clear'd himſelf in all other particulars; and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors (being conſcious of it) betooke themſelves to their wonted ſhifts to hinder the Dr. from being heard, and thereupon propoſed to ſettle a certain maintenance of 160 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> and upon that offer the buſineſs ceas'd: And the Dr. was unwilling further to trouble their Lordſhips, and ſo left the opportunity of further vindicating himſelf; the Crimes charg'd upon him (were they true, which God forbid) being of ſuch Antiquity, which alone had been a ſufficient anſwer to any rationall Man.</p>
            <p>The Dr. denies that he ever demanded any Tythes, while <hi>Woods</hi> Leaſe was in being, of any that were within his Leaſe.</p>
            <p>That he muſt ever acknowledge the Juſtice and Favour of the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the late Lord Chancellor, who did offer him a Living in <hi>Northam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pton-ſhire;</hi> but he taking time to conſider of it, was ſhortly after diſabled by a fracture of his Leg to attend it, in which time that being diſpoſed of, the Dr. waited ſeverall times after upon his Lordſhip to receive his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, but his Lordſhip did never offer or deſire (though the Proſecutors urg'd it) that the Dr. ſhould reſigne his Living before he had another, and hopes he never gave his Grace of <hi>Canterbury</hi> any cauſe to refuſe him a Living; for if the Proſecutors would remember, his Grace took notice in the preſence of the Lord Chancellor of their abuſe in that they had lately preſented ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Articles againſt the Dr. to his Grace, who order'd him to give an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thereunto, which was done accordingly, but they dealt there with his Grace as in all other places, deſigning only to beſpatter, and never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an anſwer, but wav'd his Grace, and clamour'd in other places; and if true (as they pretend) that his Grace hath ſo bad an opinion of the Dr. he is ſtill willing to refer himſelf to any determination of his Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 11.</note> That the Libellers do well diſcover themſelves in making their Judgments of the Providence of God by their own Chriſtian aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion in the 13th page, which deſerves no other Anſwer, but its well known he had the Charitable aſſiſtance of ſeverall worthy perſons.</p>
            <p>And for the Bone-ſetter, the Dr. offered him 5 <hi>l.</hi> only for his pains, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alſo paid his Apothecary his full Bill, and 5 <hi>l.</hi> to another Chyrurgeon, whom he deſired to attend, ſaying he could not; and fees to two other Chyrurgeons, but denies he owed the Bone-ſetter any thing before, he being
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30028:5"/>then an Apprentice to an Apothecary, and the D. ſatisfied his Maſter, and him too; and he (being as unreaſonable as the Libellers) firſt demanding 100 <hi>l.</hi> and afterwards ſaying he would not abate any thing of 50 l. he cauſed the Bailiff to arreſt the Dr. coming out of the Church on Sunday, who put in Bayle to his Action, and afterwards (without pleading any priviledge) offered to try it with him, (for ſeverall Chyrurgeons ſaid they would teſtifie the render was ſufficient) but he then readily accepted of the 5 l. and the Dr. long ſince had his generall Releaſe, and alſo gave full ſatisfaction to Mr. <hi>Weldon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 12.</note> It appears by their own Libell (as the truth was) That Sir <hi>Adam Browne,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Howard</hi> were only to arbitrate Arrears of Tythes in difference, but not one word of any Report to be made by them, but ſince they were pleaſed to do it <hi>ex parte,</hi> and the Libellers have made ſuch uſe of it, he ſuppoſeth it will not be unbecoming him to offer ſome Anſwer to it, which is, That though by writing he acquainted them, he hoped he ſhould be able ſhortly to attend them, if they would pleaſe to appoint a meeting at the Vicaridge Houſe, for that he was not able to wait upon them any where elſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great prejudice; yet within a few days they ſent for him to the <hi>George-Inn,</hi> where (being unable to go without Crutches) he did attend them till 10 of the Clock at Night, though to his great pain and indiſpoſition, the Chyrurgeon telling him it was enough to endanger the loſs of his Limbe: The rule they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by in their Arbitration was, to give the Vicar a third part of the Tenth of their Rent, which was much to the Doctors prejudice in many caſes, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly in one <hi>George Phillips,</hi> whoſe Tythes in kind came to a great deal more then was due by their Rule, yet he accepted of it, but ſome of the Pariſhioners where the Rule was againſt them, refuſed to pay what they determined: in particuler <hi>Henry Ledgold</hi> who was Awarded by them to pay 30 <hi>s.</hi> but he told them he would ſpend 30 <hi>l.</hi> firſt; and <hi>John Aldridge,</hi> whoſe Tythes according to the ſaid Rule came to 3 <hi>l.</hi> and the <hi>Dr.</hi> was perſwaded by them to take 30 <hi>s.</hi> which is not paid to this day: And ſeveral others (knowing that the Rule was againſt them) would not appear; and moſt of their time was ſpent in perſwading the <hi>Dr.</hi> to take leſs then his agreements, which though he conceived was not within the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Reference, yet to gratifie thoſe perſons (who had only power of Perſwaſion, none of Compulſion) he did agree unto; being willing at their Requeſt, to take 4 <hi>l.</hi> of <hi>Thomas George,</hi> of the 11 <hi>l.</hi> which the Court gave him, and by 20 <hi>s.</hi> a Month, but not a peny of it (though the 4. Months are paſt) is paid to this day; Remitting <hi>William Henderſon</hi> 2 <hi>l.</hi> though he had good Security, <hi>Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>frey Matthew</hi> 3 l. <hi>David Hore</hi> 2 l. <hi>Thomas Barber</hi> about 1 l. and ſeveral others to the value of about 40 <hi>l.</hi> and all charges the Dr. was at in ſueing ſeveral perſons, and there being ſome who then made complaints, which he deſired might have been heard, and that he might anſwer them, the Referrees utterly denied it, ſaying, it concern'd not them, for that they only deſired to make all Friends, and would not hear any thing but matter of Tythes, and therefore he (having no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Report, nor hearing of any till it was given in) conceives not upon what ground the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e could be any evidence for that part of the Report, whereby he is charg'd to impoſe by any undue means, to draw any of the Inhabitants into Exorbit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Agreements, Poenal Bills or Judgments, by Arreſting or keeping them in duran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> for that matter being ſeriouſly examin'd in a Court upon full evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where it properly belonged, the Dr. was acquitted of it, and did then
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30028:5"/>offer the Referees to ſatisfie them in it, but they (as he underſtood by thorn) thought it not fit to ravell into it after that had been ſetled in a due courſe of Law, therefore the Dr. takes it as his great unhappineſs, if that in the Libell be a true Copy, that they did not give him leave to ſatisfie them, which he doubts not to have done, and could ſtill do, or any indifferent perſons, notwithſtanding the Malice of his Enemies; and whereas they conceive the Dr. in ſome meaſure hath been the occaſion of the non-payment of what was his juſt dues, and for a ground of their belief, alledge that every perſon before them willingly ſubmitted to whatſoever they determined, the Dr. craves leave to put them in remembrance that their foundation was wholly miſtaken; for that they cannot but call to mind, and he hath ſeverall Witneſſes to prove that <hi>Ledgold</hi> aforeſaid (to name no more) did peremptorily deny it; And beſides there are many the Dr. ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſued, who were, and ſtill are, many years in Arrears, therefore could not (under their favour) be the Occaſion of the Non-payment of his Tythes, and doubtleſs the offence taken was occaſioned by the inſinuation of his inveterate Enemies, he never being heard in the reaſon that induc'd him to Sue them, which had they been acquainted with, they could not but have agreed the Dr. had good cauſe to Sue for his Dues; and till the laſt Night of their Meeting he did not perceive they were diſſatisfied in his proceedings, and the Refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rees (for what reaſon the Dr. knows not) could not poſſibly be prevailed with by him to meet either in the Veſtry, or any other place, but in the only Houſe in Town where all the miſchief againſt him hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived; Wherein the Dr. and his Agents having received many Affronts in the time of the reference and the Maſter of the Houſe having formerly Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticled againſt him in the Eccleſiaſtical Court, it was reaſon enough (had he been well) to have repaired to his own Houſe after 12 of Clock at Night, there being no perſons having any difference, who waited for any determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it.</p>
            <p>As for Mr. <hi>Joyner,</hi> The Dr. knows not the value of his Tythes, but a knowing Man in the Pariſh affirmed they were worth 10 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> thoſe years when he had 600 Sheep, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as for the ſecond party mentioned, the Dr. at the firſt meeting deſired that concern might be proceeded upon; and another time ſuppoſing it would come on, brought Councell in Order to it.</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>Bowyer</hi> the Dr. had no reaſon to refer that difference, a Wiſe and Prudent Perſon (and a Juſtice of the Peace in the ſaid County) after much time ſpent, and hearing Witneſſes on both ſides, having made his Award therein, and Sir <hi>Adam Browne</hi> declaring his diſlike thereof.</p>
            <p>The Dr, though there are now above 300 in Arrears, hath ſcarcely ſued one of an 100, nor they, till ſeverall times ſummon'd to pay, not ſo much yearly, as they ſpend weekly in an Ale houſe. And therefore who is moſt oppreſt, and have moſt reaſon to ſupplicate the Honourable Court of Parliament, they who unjuſtly detain their Tythes, and many of them from a Principle that they are not due, or the Dr. who is neceſſitated for Bread, without which he and his Family muſt languiſh, or be forced to ſue for ſuch trifles, the profits of his Living ariſing out of no other payments but ſuch ſmall Tythes.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:30028:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Dr. admires they ſhould cloſe their Libell with ſo falſe an invention as the pretended Debauchery at <hi>Newington,</hi> for he ſolemnly affirms, as in the preſence God, Angells and Men, that there is not one ſyllable of it true, and he offers to execute that upon himſelf, which they unreaſonably deſire to be done, if by any Credible Witneſſes they convict him of it. But this is like the reſt of their un-chriſtian dealings; having lately again Cryed him in Scorne in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place, and interrupted him in Divine Service, by publiſhing that as an Order of His Majeſty and Councell, which was never made by them. All which might have been juſtly anſwered in their own Language, or with perſonall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminations, there being ſufficient ground to do it, but they having in proſecution of their continued Malice towards the Dr. thus publickly blaſted him in Print, it was thought fit to anſwer the Fact in particulers charged, to manifeſt to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and ſatisfie the Chriſtian Reader, what deſigns have been carried on to ruine him in his Reputation, knowing they could not otherwiſe hurt him. And as for their General Accuſations, when reduced to particulers, he doubts not but to give them as full an anſwer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30028:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
